<?xml version="1.0"?>


<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!--   Modeling, Functions, and Graphs   -->
<!--           4th                                     -->
<!-- Copyright (C) Katherine Yoshiwara      -->

<exercises xml:id="section-7-5-exercises"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Problem Set 7.5</title>

<subexercises><title>Warm Up</title>

<exercisegroup cols="2"><introduction><p>For Problems 1-4, solve. Round your answers to hundredths.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="1"><statement><p><m>4.6(x-3)^{1.8}+12=18</m></p></statement>
<answer><p>4.16</p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="2"><statement><p><m>2x^2-4.7x=3.8</m></p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="3"><statement><p><m>28(1.65)^{-0.3t} = 2.53</m></p></statement>
<answer><p>16</p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="4"><statement><p><m>5(10)^x=30</m></p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup><introduction><p>For Problems 5<ndash/>8, find an equation for the line with the given properties.</p>
</introduction> 

<exercise number="5"><statement><p>slope <m>= \dfrac{-2}{3}</m>, <m>y</m>-intercept is <m>(0,-1)</m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>y=\dfrac{-2}{3}x-1</m></p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="6"><statement><p>slope <m>=-2</m>, passes through <m>(-1,2)</m></p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="7"><statement><p>passes through <m>(0,4)</m> and <m>(2,3)</m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>y=\dfrac{-1}{2}x+4</m></p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="8"><statement><p>passes through <m>(-3,0)</m> and <m>(0,-5)</m></p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>
</subexercises>

<subexercises><title>Skills Practice</title>

<exercisegroup cols="2"><introduction><p>For Problems 9 and 10, find an exponential function that has the given values.</p>
</introduction>

<exercise number="9"><statement><p><m>P(0)=8,~P(5)=0.25</m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>P(x)=8(0.5)^x</m></p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="10"><statement><p><m>f(2)=9, ~f(3)=12</m></p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup cols="2"><introduction><p>For Problems 11 and 12, find a formula for the exponential function.</p>
</introduction>

<exercise number="11"><statement><sidebyside width="75%"><image source="images/fig-3halves-times-3-to-x-over-5"><description>mystery exponential growth</description></image></sidebyside></statement>
<answer><p><m>y=1.5(3){x/5}</m></p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="12"><statement><sidebyside width="65%"><image source="images/fig-8fifths-times-5-to-neg-x-over-3"><description>mystery exponential decay</description></image></sidebyside></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup cols="2"><introduction><p>For Problems 13 and 14,<ol marker="a.">
    <li>fit a linear function to the points,</li>
    <li>fit an exponential function to the points,</li>
    <li>graph both functions in the same window.</li></ol></p></introduction>

<exercise number="13"><statement><p><m>(0,2.6)</m>, <m>(1,1.3)</m></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol marker="a.">
    <li><m>y=2.6-1.3x</m></li>
    <li><m>y=2.5(0,5)^x</m></li>
    <li><sidebyside width="80%"><image source="images/fig-lin-and-exp-fit"><description>graph</description></image></sidebyside></li></ol></p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="14"><statement><p><m>(-2,0.75),~(4,6)</m></p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

</subexercises>

<subexercises><title>Applications</title>

<exercisegroup><introduction><p>For Problems 15-18, write a growth or decay formula for the exponential function.  Then find the percent growth or decay rate.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="15"><statement><p>A population starts with 2000 and has a doubling time of 5 years.</p></statement>
<answer><p><m>P(t)=2000(2^{t/5};~</m> 14.9%</p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="16"><statement><p>You have 10 grams of a radioactive isotope whose half-life is 42 years.</p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="17"><statement><p>A certain medication has a half-life of 18 hours in the body. You are given an initial dose of <m>D_0</m> mg.</p></statement>
<answer><p><m>D(t)=D_0(0,5^{t/18};~</m> 3.8%</p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="18"><statement><p>The doubling time of a certain financial investment is 8 years. You invest an amount <m>M_0</m>.</p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercise number="19"><statement><p>In 1798, the English political economist Thomas R. Malthus claimed that human populations, unchecked by environmental or social constraints, double every 25 years, regardless of the initial population size.<ol marker="a.">
        <li><p>Write a growth law for human populations under these conditions.</p></li>
        <li><p>What is the growth rate in unconstrained conditions?</p></li>
    </ol></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="2">
    <li><p><m>P = P_0 (2)^{t/25 }</m></p></li>
    <li><p>2.81%</p></li>
</ol></p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="20"><statement><p>David Sifry observed in 2005 that over the previous two years, the number of Weblogs, or blogs, was doubling every 5 months. (Source: www.sifry.com/alerts/archives)<ol marker="a.">
    <li><p>Write a formula for the number of blogs <m>t</m> years after January 2005, assuming it continues to grow at the same rate.</p></li>
    <li><p>What is the growth rate for the number of blogs?</p></li>
    </ol></p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="21"><statement><p>Radioactive potassium-42, which is used by cardiologists as a tracer, decays at a rate of 5.4% per hour.
<ol marker="a.">
    <li><p>Find the half-life of potassium-42.</p></li>
    <li><p>How long will it take for three-fourths of the sample to decay? For seven-eighths of the sample?</p></li>
    <li><p>Suppose you start with 400 milligrams of potassium-42. Using your answers to (a) and (b), make a rough sketch of the decay function.</p></li>
    </ol></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol marker="a." cols="2">
    <li><p><m>\dfrac{\log {(0.5)}}{\log {(0.946)}}\approx 12.5 </m> hours</p></li>
    <li><p>25 hours</p></li>
    <li><sidebyside width="40%"><image source="images/fig-hw-7-5-11ans"><description>decay</description></image></sidebyside></li>
</ol></p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="22"><statement><p>Caffeine leaves the body at a rate of 15.6% each hour. Your first cup of coffee in the morning has 100 mg of caffeine.<ol marker="a.">
    <li><p>How long will it take before you have 50 mg of that caffeine in your body?</p></li>
    <li><p>How long will it take before you have 25 mg of that caffeine in your body?</p></li>
    <li><p>Using your answers to (a) and (b), make a rough sketch of the decay function.</p></li>
    </ol></p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="23"><statement><p>Dichloro-diphenyl-trichloroethane (DDT) is a pesticide that was used in the middle decades of the twentieth century to control malaria. After 1945, it was also widely used on crops in the United States, and as much as one ton might be sprayed on a single cotton field. However, after the toxic effects of DDT on the environment began to appear, the chemical was banned in 1972.<ol marker="a.">
    <li><p>A common estimate for the half-life of DDT in the soil is 15 years. Write a decay law for DDT in the soil.</p></li>
    <li><p>In 1970, many soil samples in the United States contained about 0.5 mg of DDT per kg of soil. The NOAA (National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration) safe level for DDT in the soil is 0.008 mg/kg. When will DDT content in the soil be reduced to a safe level?</p></li>
    </ol></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol marker="a.">
    <li><m>D(t)=D_0(0.5)^{t/15}</m></li>
    <li>After 89.5 years, or in 2060</li></ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="24"><statement><p>In 1986, the inflation rate in Bolivia was 8000% annually. The unit of currency in Bolivia is the boliviano.<ol marker="a.">
    <li><p>Write a formula for the price of an item as a function of time. Let <m>P_0</m> be its initial price.</p></li>
    <li><p>How long did it take for prices to double? Give both an exact value and a decimal approximation rounded to two decimal places.</p></li>
    <li><p>Suppose <m>P_0 = 5</m> bolivianos. Graph your function in the window <m>\text{Xmin} = 0</m>, <m>\text{Xmax} = 0.94</m>, <m>\text{Ymin} = 0</m>, <m>\text{Ymax} = 100</m>.</p></li>
    <li><p>Use <term>intersect</term> to verify that the price of the item doubles from 5 to 10 bolivianos, from 10 to 20, and from 20 to 40 in equal periods of time.</p></li>
    </ol></p></statement></exercise>

<exercisegroup><introduction><p>In Problems 25 and 26,<ol marker="a.">
        <li><p>Write a decay law for the isotope.</p></li>
        <li><p>Use the decay law to answer the question. (Round to the nearest ten years.)</p></li>
    </ol></p></introduction>

<exercise number="25"><statement><p>In living organisms, carbon-14 occurs with a fixed ratio to nonradioactive carbon-12. After a plant or animal dies, the carbon-14 decays into stable carbon with a halflife of 5730 years. When samples from the Shroud of Turin were analyzed in 1988, they were found to have 91.2% of their original carbon-14. How old were those samples in 1988?</p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="2">
    <li><p><m>A = A_0 \left(\dfrac{1}{2} \right)^{t/5730}</m></p></li>
    <li><p>About 760 years old</p></li>
</ol></p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="26"><statement><p>Rubidium-strontium radioactive dating is used in geologic studies to measure the age of minerals. Rubidium-87 decays into strontium-87 with a half-life of 48.8 billion years. Several meteors were found to have 93.7% of their original rubidium. How old are the meteors?</p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup><introduction><p>For Problems 27-30, use the following formula for compound interest. If <m>P</m> dollars is invested at an annual interest rate <m>r</m> (expressed as a decimal) compounded <m>n</m> times yearly, the amount <m>A</m> after <m>t</m> years is given by
    <me>A=P \left(1+\dfrac{r}{n}\right)^{nt}</me>
 </p></introduction>

<exercise number="27"><statement><p>What rate of interest is required so that $1000 will yield $1900 after 5 years if the interest rate is compounded monthly?</p></statement>
<answer><p>12.9%</p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="28"><statement><p>What rate of interest is required so that $400 will yield $600 after 3 years if the interest rate is compounded quarterly?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="29"><statement><p>How long will it take a sum of money to triple if it is invested at 10% compounded daily?</p></statement>
<answer><p>About 11 years</p></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="30"><statement><p>How long will it take a sum of money to increase by a factor of 5 if it is invested at 10% compounded quarterly?</p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

</subexercises>

</exercises>